A Finding Aid to the Nancy Douglas Bowditch and Brush Family papers, circa 1860-1985, in the Archives of American Art AAA.bowdnanc
Archives of American Art
- Writings and Notes, circa 1900-1975; Series 4; 1 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  - by Others, circa 1900-circa 1970s; 4.2
    - Notes by Barry Faulkner, circa 1941 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Writings by William Robert Pearmain, circa 1909 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Poem and Song by Gra, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Concerning Various Artists, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Lists of Works of Art by Brush, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Artwork, 1898-1950; Series 5; 4 Folders Boxes 4, 9-10
  Artwork is by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, William Robert Pearmain, and George de Forest Brush. Nancy Douglas Bowditch's work consists of one sketch, one study, and three completed drawings of William Robert Pearmain and Alan Seeger. Pearmain's artwork comprises twenty-four sketches including one watercolor, twelve studies, and forty-two completed drawings. Also found is one pencil sketch by Brush.
  - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, Pencil Sketches, 1912-1950 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - George de Forest Brush, Pencil Sketch, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Oversized item housed in OV 9
  - William Robert Pearmain, Pencil Sketches and Drawings, 1898-1909 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Oversized items housed in OV 9-10
  - William Robert Pearmain, Tempera and Oil Sketches, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Sketch by George de Forest Brush and Oversized Sketches by William Robert Pearmain, circa 1900-1912 (Box OV9)
    Scanned with Box 4, F24 and F25
  - Oversized Sketches by William Robert Pearmain, 1898-1909 (Box OV10)
    Scanned with Box 4, F25
- Printed Material, 1889-1974; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  Printed materials include clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, calling cards, and other materials concerning Nancy Douglas Bowditch, George de Forest Brush, Barry Faulkner, Stephen Parrish, and Abbot Handerston Thayer.
  - Archives of American Art Publications, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Articles Concerning Nancy Douglas Bowditch, 1965-1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Articles Concerning George de Forest Brush, 1889-1971 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Book Reviews, The Joyous Painter, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Calling Cards, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Files Kept by William Robert Pearmain, 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Concerning Nancy Douglas Bowditch, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Concerning George de Forest Brush, 1923-1941 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Concerning Cornish Colony Artists, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - General, 1913-1973 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Dust Jacket, The Joyous Painter, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 4)
    - George de Forest Brush, 1930-1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Barry Faulkner, 1956-1967 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Stephen Parish, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Abbot Handerson Thayer, undated; 1923 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Mark Twain Quarterly, Winter 1957 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; 1912 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, by George de Forest Brush, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Brush Family Home Building Files, 1910-1971; Series 7; 10 Folders Boxes 4, 8
  This series contains materials relating to two homes of the Brush family: Brushwood, built by William Robert Pearmain, and a logcabin in Dublin, NH. Materials include plans, a map of Dublin, New Hampshire, Stave Church inspirations used by Pearmain to design the house, photographs, and a watercolor of Brushwood by Nancy.
  - Brushwood (Box 4)
    - Plan of Brushwood, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      photograph of original
    - Map of Dublin, New Hampshire, 1970 September 18 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Examples of Stave Churches, undated; circa 1910 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Photographs of Home, 1911 October (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Photographs of Home, 1923-1924 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      taken by Harold Bowditch
    - Photographs of Interior, circa 1910s (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Watercolor of Brushwood, by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1910s (Box 4, Folder 53)
      Oversized material housed in Box 8
  - Log Cabin (Box 4)
    - Sketch, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 54)
      photocopy
    - Photographs of Construction, 1971 August-November (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Photographs, after 1971 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Oversized Watercolor, circa 1910s (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Oversized item scanned with Box 4, F53
- Scrapbooks, circa 1907-circa 1985; Series 8; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 5, 8
  Found are five scrapbooks compiled by members of the Brush, Pearmain, and Bowditch families. The majority of the albums consist of photographs and reproductions of works of art by George de Forest Brush and William Robert Pearmain. There are also photographs of exhibitions of Brush's art and of installations. One scrapbook contains family photographs organized by date by Harold Bowditch.
  - Scrapbook Owned by Lo. Halaby (Box 5)
    - Letter, circa 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of Works of Art by George de Forest Brush, circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Reproductions of Works of Art by George de Forest Brush, circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
      loose materials tucked into album
  - Scrapbook by William Robert Pearmain (Box 5)
    - Fragments, circa 1911 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of Works of Art by William Robert Pearmain (Box 5)
    - Album Cover, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Photographs and Obituary, circa 1950s; 1916 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Sketch, circa 1907 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Album of Exhibition of Works of Art by George de Forest Brush (Box 5)
    - Album Cover, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Printed Material, 1968; undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Photograps of Works of Art and Installations, 1968; undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Photographs of Reception, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Photographs of Installations, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Polly Pearmain's photos
    - Photographs of Reception, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook by Harold Bowditch (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Oversized items housed in Box 8
    - Oversized items from Harold Bowditch Scrapbook, circa 1920s (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1860-1979; Series 9; 1 Linear feet Boxes 5-7, 11
  Found are family photographs of the Brush family, snapshots, vacations, portraits, interiors, studios, buildings, pets and animals, family events, and of works of art. Among those photographed include George de Forest and Mittie Taylor Whelpley Brush and their children; Nancy Bowditch's children and grandchildren; the Pearmain family; the wedding of Clara Clemens with her father Samuel Clemens; and the Thayer children, their homes, and sleeping huts. A portrait of Nancy as a young woman was taken by Jean Clemens and has a love letter written by Robert Pearmain on verso. Also found are copies of photographs used in a biography of George de Forest Brush by Joan Morgan entitled George de Forest Brush, 1855-1941: Master of the American Renaissance (1985).
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. Photographs of works of art have not been scanned.
  - Portraits (Box 5)
    - George de Forest Brush, 1898-1926 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Mittie Taylor Whelpley Brush, 1870-1912 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Mary Brush and Children, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Brush Children, 1898-1908 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Georgia Brush, circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Jane Brush, 1908-1918 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Mary Brush, 1898-1918 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1898-1905 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      Nancy Douglas Bowditch as a Child
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      Includes photographs taken by Jean Clemens of Nancy as a young woman. Verso contains love letters written to Nancy by William Robert Pearmain.
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 28)
      Nancy with a child, probably Polly Peamrain
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1930s-1964 (Box 5, Folder 29)
      Nancy as an adult
    - Tribbie Brush, 1898-1909 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Nancy and William Robert Pearmain, 1907 August (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Nancy and Harold Bowditch, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Mary "Polly" Pearmain Marlowe, circa late 1920s (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Clifford Seymour Brush and Gerome Brush II, 1957 December (Box 5, Folder 34)
      Gerome Brush's children
    - Harold Bowditch, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Lillie Brush, circa 1890s (Box 5, Folder 36)
      George de Forest Brush's sister
    - Dr. James Davenport Whelpley, circa 1890s (Box 5, Folder 37)
      copyprint
    - William Robert Pearmain, 1892 September; circa 1895 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Pearmain Siblings, 1888-1904 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      Margaret, Jack, Edward, and William Robert with their mother, Alice
    - Gladys Thayer (Galla), circa 1909 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - F. L. W., 1936 or 1937 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Unidentified, circa 1890-1900 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Weddings (Box 5)
    - Clara Clemens (?), 1910 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      Clara Clemens, Samuel Clemens, Jarvis Langdon, Jean Clemens, Mr. Twitchell
    - Nancy and Robert, 1909 September 11 (Box 5, Folder 44-45)
    - Nancy with Bridesmaids, 1909 September 11 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      Margaret Pearmain and Tribbie Brush
    - Gerald Thayer and Alina Wallerman, before 1916 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Graduations and Reunions (Box 5)
    - Wellsley, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Snapshots (Box 5)
    - George de Forest Brush with Children and Grandchildren, 1892-circa 1930s (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - George de Forest Brush with Children and Grandchildren, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      framed photograph
    - George de Forest Brush with Sons-in-Law, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - George de Forest Brush Painting Outside, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Mittle Taylor Whelpley Brush with her Children, 1909-1930s (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch (?) as a Young Child, circa 1890 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch with her Children, 1911-1969 (Box 5, Folder 56)
      with Polly and George
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch with Family and Friends, 1966-1973 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Harold and Nancy Douglas Bowditch, 1919-1948 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Harold and Nancy Douglas Bowditch with Their Grandchildren, late 1930s (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Harold Bowditch, 1923; undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Harold Bowditch with his Children, early 1920s (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Bowditch and Pearmain Children, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 62)
      Polly, George, Henry and Martha
    - Brush Sisters, 1907-1911; circa 1915 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      Mary, Thea and Jane
    - Mary Brush in World War I Service Uniform, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Clifford and Gerry Brush, circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Faith Lea Storer, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Philip Whelpley, circa 1909 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      standing in front of Thayer family home
    - Whelpley Family Members, circa 1900-1952 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Pearmain Family Members, circa 1909 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Bowditch Family Members, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      likely Harold Bowditch's mother, Selma Bowditch
    - Hildegarde and Gerard Henderson, 1905 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Gerard Henderson, Georgie Brush, and Unknown, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      likely Hildegarde Henderson
    - Thayer Family, 1904-1909 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      Mary, Gladys, Gerald and Abbot Handerson
    - Miss Lyons, Mr. Paine and Gerome Brush, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      Samuel Clemens' secretary and biographer
    - Ilka Howells, circa 1890 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1900-1976 (Box 5, Folder 76-77)
      Identified photographs, relationships to the Brush family unknown
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1900-1950s (Box 5, Folder 78-79)
      Unidentified photographs
  - Gravestones (Box 5)
    - George de Forest Brush, 1969 August (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Animals (Box 5)
    - Family Dogs and Chickens, 1902-circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Cars (Box 5)
    - Cars, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Studios (Box 5)
    - George de Forest Brush's Italian Studio and Garden, circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Pearmain's Paris Studio (?), circa 1905-1908 March 21 (Box 5, Folder 84-85)
    - George de Forest Brush in his Studio, circa 1910s (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Interiors (Box 5)
    - Russels Camp, circa 1900 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - 44 Harvard Avenue, Brookline, MA, circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 88)
      Harold and Nancy Bowditch's Home
    - 12 Pine, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 89)
      Includes Baha'i art and portraits
    - Unidentified, circa 1905-1969 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Theatrical Costume (Box 5)
    - Brush Family and Friends in Italy, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Gerome Brush in Soldier Girl, circa 1906 or 1907 (Box 5, Folder 92)
      play written by Gerome Brush
    - Mary and Jane Brush, circa 1910s (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Harold Bowditch in School Play, circa 1905 or 1915 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Unidentified, circa 1900s (Box 5, Folder 95)
      probably Pearmain family in Medival costume
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch in Colonial and Post-Civil War Dresses, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch and David Marlowe as Mr. Haseltine, 1964 June 13 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Nancy Douglas Bowditch in Native American Dress, circa 1963 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Polly Marlowe, circa 1960s-1979s (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Polly Marlowe and Kathleen Bowditch, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Alina Thayer and Mary Brush, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified, circa 1909 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Buildings and Homes (Box 6)
    - George de Forest Brush's Birthplace, circa 1860 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      print of original
    - Brush Home in Florence, Italy, circa 1907 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Farm in Dublin, New Hampshire, 1910-1920s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Putnam Camp, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 295 Commonwealth Avenue, Boston, MA, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      William Robert Pearmain's family home
    - Groton School Dormitory, circa 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Thayer Home and Sleeping Huts, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Douglas Volk's House in Lowell, ME, 1911 August (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Churches and Baha'i Temples, 1952-1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified, 1908-1950s (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Outdoors (Box 6)
    - Crawford Notch, New Hampshire, 1911 August (Box 6, Folder 11)
      White Mountains
    - Dublin, New Hampshire, 1911 October (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Bedford, MA, circa 1900s (Box 6, Folder 13)
      view of Charles River
  - Travel (Box 6)
    - Paris, France, circa 1908 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Gibraltar, circa 1908 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Cyprus, Greece and Aegean Sea, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Florence, Italy, undated; 1908 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Naples, Italy, 1908 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Palermo and San Reggio, Italy, 1907-1909 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Works of Art (Box 6)
    - Polly Pearmain Marlowe with Works of Art by her Parents, 1969 August (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Bust of Nathaniel Bowditch by Ball Hughes, circa 1900 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - by Nancy Douglas Bowditch, circa 1900-1970s (Box 6, Folder 22-25)
    - by George de Forest Brush, circa 1900-1970s (Box 6, Folder 26-32)
      Oversized material housed in OV 11
    - by William Robert Pearmain, 1909-1910 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - by Douglas Volk, 1909 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1910s (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Duplicates, 1888-1939 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Duplicates, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Negatives and Slides, circa 1910s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 2-7)
    - Notes and Photo Enclosures, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - George de Forest Brush, 1855-1941: Master of the American Renaissance (1985), by Joan Morgan (Box 7)
    - Prints Used in Book, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Photograph of Work of Art by Brush, circa 1900 (Box 11)
    Material from Box 6, F26